New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors; Records apap315
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors Records
1950-2009
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors
apap315
36.5 cubic ft.
The records of the New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors trace the development of mental healthcare throughout the state from the early 1950s through the beginning of the twenty-first century. Established in the mid-1970s, the Conference's records include correspondence, memos, meeting minutes, reports, and manuals that chronicle the efforts of mental health professionals as they encourage local, county, and state agencies to provide quality, affordable services for persons living with mental illness, chemical dependency, and/or developmental disability.
Access
Access to this record group is mainly unrestricted; the exceptions are folders 20 through 26 in Series 5, Box 2. Researchers seeking access to this material should contact the head of archives.
Acquisition Information
All items in the New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors Records were donated by the Conference to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, in 2009.
Organizational Sketch
The New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors (NYSCLMHD) specializes in advocacy for the mentally ill, the developmentally disabled, and/or people with chemical dependencies. The Conference also extends outreach efforts to the families of those they serve. Its efforts focus on ensuring that people with various mental health needs have quality, affordable care, guiding formation of local and state policies to make sure that they are as current and relevant as possible. [1]
The NYSCLMHD was formed in 1976 under Article 41 of the state Mental Hygiene Law, which covers local and unified services. Article 41 was “designed to enable and encourage local governments to develop in the community preventive, rehabilitative, and treatment services offering continuity of care” and stresses the need for cooperation among local, county, and state governments in order to provide the best level of mental healthcare. [2] As such, the Conference— operating at the county level—serves as a link between statewide and local services, confirming that policies are carried out efficiently in the realms of clinical and rehabilitative work. The Conference opened its Albany, New York headquarters in 1978, and as an affiliate of the New York State Association of Counties (NYSAC), it was originally located in the NYSAC building on State Street. [3] The Conference continues to be affiliated with NYSAC but has since moved to a different building in downtown Albany.
The NYSCLMHD, which is a not-for-profit organization, oversees a complex and extensive network of professionals, requiring participation by mental health directors and commissioners from New York State’s 57 counties and New York City*. [4] These are the people who are already coordinating mental health care services in their own counties and therefore have the knowledge and background to correlate services between local, county, and state agencies. Over the years they have worked closely with the New York State Office of Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities, Office of Mental Health, Division of Alcoholism and Alcohol Abuse, and Division of Substance Abuse as they analyze the state’s mental healthcare system and make recommendations for improvement. Daily operations are overseen by the Conference’s executive director, who in turn reports to the executive committee and chairperson. The executive committee, which meets monthly, is made up of past and present committee chairpersons, current officers, and regional representatives. All members meet twice a year at conferences, and officers are elected for two-year terms, as per the Conference’s bylaws. [5]
The Conference has devoted itself to a vast number of projects since its inception in the mid-1970s. A sample of its work includes children’s mental welfare, adult housing needs, affordable services, and care of the mentally ill during and after prison sentences. Over the years, members have both sponsored and attended many workshops and conferences designed to enhance the skills of those working on behalf of the mentally ill, chemically dependent, and developmentally disabled. It also continues to focus effort on bringing greater understanding of mental health issues to the general public as well as to key professions, such as law enforcement and education, so that people with special needs can be more efficiently integrated into everyday life.
*New York State officially has 62 counties; New York City’s five boroughs are each considered to be a separate county. (See www.nysegov.com)
[1] New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors, Inc. “About Us.” Accessed 18 January 2011 from http://www.clmhd.org/aboutus.aspx.
[2] Justia US Law. “2006 New York Code: Declaration of Purpose. Article 41.01.” Accessed 28 February 2011 from http://law.justia.com/newyork/codes/2006/mental-hygiene/mhy041.01_41.01.html.
[3] Background information on Conference's formation/early days, Series 1 Administrative, Box 1, Folder 7 New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors Records, 1950-2008. M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University Libraries, University at Albany, State University of New York.
[4] New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors, Inc. Home page. Accessed 15 February 2011 from http://www.clmhd.org.
[5] Background information on Conference's formation/early days, Series 1 Administrative, Box 1, Folder 7 New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors Records, 1950-2008. M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University Libraries, University at Albany, State University of New York.
Scope and Contents
The records of the New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors (NYSCLMHD) contain meeting minutes, correspondence, reports, and newsletters documenting the founding and day-to-day activities of the group, including original by-laws and articles of incorporation. There are also records of many of the NYSCLMHD’s specific projects from the late 1970s through the early 2000s, such as managed care/Medicaid/special needs plans, grant applications, juvenile care issues, housing concerns, partnerships with other organizations, disaster preparedness, and care of mental needs patients in prison.
Researchers will also find some materials on the history of mental health care in the state of New York. In addition, there are documents pertaining to mental health professionals’ increased efforts to partner with law enforcement to achieve better understanding of those living with mental illness, developmental disabilities, or the effects of substance abuse.
In most instances, folder titles have been retained according to the record-keeping habits of the NYSCLMHD.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Administrative Files, 1950-2005, Undated
Series 2 - Chronological Files, 1995-2005, Undated
Series 3 - Office of Legislative and Government Affairs Director, 1991-2003, Undated
Series 4 - County Plans, Operations, and Government, 1980-2009, Undated
Series 5 - Projects and Committees, 1979-2001, Undated
Series 6 - Managed Care and Special Needs Plans, 1991-2000, Undated
Series 7 - Subject Files, 1985-2008, Undated
Series 8 - NYSCLMHD Newsletters, 1980-2008, Undated
Series 9 - Reports and Publications, 1982, 1989-2006, Undated
Most of the series in the New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors Records are arranged in alphabetical order. Exceptions are Series #2, Chronological Files, which are in order by date, and Series #8, NYSCLMHD Newsletters, which are also arranged by date.
Medicine and Health Care; Mental health--United States.; Mental health--Adolescent.; Mental health--New York (State); Substance abuse--Treatment--United States.; Mental illness--Treatment--United States.; Chemical dependency; Developmental disability; Albany (NY); New York (State); Correspondence; Photographs; Newsletters; Newspaper clippings; Legal documents; Manuals (instructional materials); Minutes; Bills (legislative records); Dvoskin, Joel; New York State Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors; New York State Association of Counties
- Administrative Files, 1950-2005; Undated; 1; 1.6 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically
  Scope and Contents
  The administrative files contain executive meeting minutes from the Conference’s earliest days through the late 1980s. During those years, members kept the minutes in large, hardcover binders; the archivist removed the papers from those binders for preservation purposes and placed them in acid-free folders in the order in which they appeared in the original binders. In the 1990s, Conference members began filing their meeting minutes under the heading of “chronological files” along with meeting announcements and correspondence. The chronological files became series two of this collection and researchers will find more meeting minutes there. However, there is a gap in the Conference's meeting minutes from 1989-1994.
  This series also contains founding documents such as original charters and by-laws as well as files pertaining to activities of the executive director. Please note that there are several executive committee meeting files in Series #5: Projects and Committees.
  - 340-B Prescription drugs, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Access to child psychiatry, 2002-2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Adult homes, 1999-2002 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Aid to localities fiscal system: Multi-agency request, 2003-2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Albany/Rensselaer Housing Taskforce, 2004-2005 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Annual spring meeting, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Background information on conference's formation, early days, 1976-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - By-laws binder: By-laws and rosters, 1976-1981 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - By-laws binder: Correspondence, finances, and executive committee, 1976-1982 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - By-laws binder: Executive committee cont.'d, 1976-1980 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Costs of O.M.H. psychiatric hospitals, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - County commissioners' forums, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Dual recovery coordinators, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Electronic document management systems workshops, 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Financial management policy revision, 1999-2005 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Financial reports, 2002-2003 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Greenlight Program reports, 1999-2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - History of mental health care, 1950-1980 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18-19)
  - Integrated children's service/ TAP issue, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Leadership retreat follow-up, 2003-2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
  - Medicaid neutrality, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
  - Meeting minutes, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
  - Meeting minutes, 1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
  - Meeting minutes, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
  - Meeting minutes, 1979 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
  - Meeting minutes, 1980 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Meeting minutes, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
  - Meeting minutes, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
  - Meeting minutes, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
  - Meeting minutes, 1984 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Meeting minutes, 1985 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Meeting minutes, 1986 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Meeting minutes, 1987 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Meeting minutes, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Mental Health Committee minutes, 2002 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Mental Health Glossary of Programs and Services, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Mental Hygiene Services: Partnering at the local level, 2001 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - NACBHD Fall 2005 conference (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - NYSAC Fall conference-- Health and Mental Health Committee, 2004 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - NYS Conference of Local Mental Hygiene Directors Technical Assistance Project, 2004 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Office of Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities: NYS-OPTS Analysis, 2003-2004 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Office of Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities Partnership Committee, 2003 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Officers' meetings with commissioners and legislative chairs, 2004 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - O.M.H. new initiatives- status update, 2000-2001 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Planning meeting with Commissioner Carpinello, 2004 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - PROS county role, 2003; Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - PROS outcome measures, 2003-2004 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - PROS provider agreement, 2003-2004 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - PROS regulations- comments, 2003-2004; Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Sample of Conference brochures, 1999; 2004-2005; Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Secure facilities, 2000 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Standing committee planning and protocols, Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - State Association survey, 1998 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Telemedicine/telepsychiatry, 2004 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Tuttle, Alfred: "Purposes of the Organization", Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
- Chronological Files, 1995-2005; Undated; 2; 12.0 cu. ft.
  Arranged chronologically.
  The name of this series comes right from the Conference’s own record-keeping system. In the 1990s it stopped storing meeting minutes separately in oversized binders and began interfiling them with correspondence, meeting announcements, memorandums, and treasurer’s reports in folders labeled with the current month and year. Minutes include regularly scheduled events, such as executive committee meetings, as well as ad hoc meetings. Memos include those sent by the NYSCLMHD as well as those received by the Conference from outside sources such the New York State Office of Mental Health and the Division of Alcoholism and Alcohol Abuse.
  - NYSAC correspondence, 1995 January-1995 November (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1)
  - January, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 2-3)
  - February, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 4-5)
  - March, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 6-7)
  - April, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 8-10)
  - May, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 11)
  - June, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 12-13)
  - July, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 14-15)
  - August, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 16-17)
  - September, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 18)
  - October, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 19-20)
  - November, 1995 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1)
  - December, 1995 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 2)
  - January, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 3-4)
  - February, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 5-6)
  - March, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 7-9)
  - April, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 10-12)
  - May, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 13)
  - June, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 14-16)
  - July, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 17-19)
  - August, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 20-21)
  - September, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 22)
  - October, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 23-24)
  - October, 1996 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1)
  - November, 1996 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 2)
  - December, 1996 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 3)
  - Executive committee meeting minutes, 1997 December-1999 July (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 4)
  - January, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 5)
  - February, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 6-8)
  - March, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 9-10)
  - April, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 11-15)
  - May, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 16-17)
  - June, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 18)
  - July, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 19-20)
  - August, 1997 (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1)
  - September, 1997 (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 2)
  - October, 1997 (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 3-5)
  - November, 1997 (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 6)
  - December, 1997 (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 7)
  - Technical assistance correspondence, 1997 May-1998 April (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 8-9)
  - Welfare-to-Work, 1997 January-1997 December (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 10)
  - Managed care, 1998 February-1998 May (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 11)
  - Medicaid Carveout, 1998 February (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 12)
  - Public benefit corporations, 1996 January-1996 May (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 13)
  - Welfare reform, 1998 April-1998 May (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 14)
  - Temporary Assistance for Needy Families (TANF) information, 1998 March (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 15)
  - AHLPR grant, 1998 March-1998 April (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 16)
  - 1998 Technical Assistance Plan, 1997 November (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 17)
  - January, 1998 (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 18-19)
  - February, 1998 (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 20)
  - March, 1998 (Box 4 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 21-23)
  - April, 1998 (Box 5 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1-3)
  - May, 1998 (Box 5 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 4-7)
  - June, 1998 (Box 5 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 8-9)
  - July, 1998 (Box 5 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 10-13)
  - August, 1998 (Box 5 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 14)
  - September, 1998 (Box 5 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 15-17)
  - October, 1998 (Box 5 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 18-20)
  - November, 1998 (Box 5 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 21)
  - December, 1998 (Box 6 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1-2)
  - Minutes and treasurer's reports, 1998 (Box 6 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 3)
  - January, 1999 (Box 6 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 4)
  - February, 1999 (Box 6 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 5-6)
  - March, 1999 (Box 6 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 7-8)
  - April, 1999 (Box 6 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 9-11)
  - May, 1999 (Box 6 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 12-15)
  - June, 1999 (Box 6 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 16-18)
  - July, 1999 (Box 6 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 19-20)
  - August, 1999 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1)
  - September, 1999 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 2)
  - October, 1999 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 3-5)
  - November, 1999 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 6-7)
  - December, 1999 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 8)
  - January, 2000 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 9-10)
  - February, 2000 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 11-12)
  - March, 2000 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 13-15)
  - April, 2000 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 16-18)
  - May, 2000 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 19)
  - June, 2000 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 20)
  - July, 2000 (Box 7 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 21)
  - August, 2000 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1)
  - September, 2000 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 2)
  - October, 2000 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 3)
  - November, 2000 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 4)
  - December, 2000 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 5)
  - January, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 6)
  - February, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 7)
  - March, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 8)
  - April, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 9-10)
  - May, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 11)
  - June, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 12-13)
  - July, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 14-15)
  - August, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 16)
  - September, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 17)
  - October, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 18-19)
  - November, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 20)
  - December, 2001 (Box 8 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 21)
  - December, 2001 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1-2)
  - January, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 3)
  - February, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 4)
  - March, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 5-6)
  - April, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 7)
  - May, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 8-10)
  - June, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 11)
  - July, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 12)
  - August, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 13-14)
  - September, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 15-17)
  - October, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 18)
  - November, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 19)
  - December, 2002 (Box 9 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 20-21)
  - January, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1)
  - February, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 2-4)
  - March, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 5-6)
  - April, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 7-9)
  - May, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 10)
  - June, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 11)
  - July, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 12)
  - August, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 13)
  - September, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 14-15)
  - October, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 16-17)
  - November, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 18)
  - December, 2003 (Box 10 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 19-20)
  - January, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 1-2)
  - February, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 3)
  - March, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 4-5)
  - April, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 6-7)
  - May, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 8)
  - June, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 9-11)
  - July, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 12)
  - August, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 13)
  - September, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 14-15)
  - October, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 16-17)
  - November, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 18-19)
  - December, 2004 (Box 11 (2-Chronological Files), Folder 20-21)